Guide to the Martin and Naomi Warren Papers, 1952-2010 MS 739
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Martin and Naomi Warren Papers
1952-2010
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Warren, Helen; Spector, Helen Warren; Warren, Martin
MS 739
.25 Linear Feet 1 box
This collection consists of one box containing news clippings, membership cards, photographs, and biographical information documenting the lives of Martin and Naomi Warren from 1952-2010.
Scope and Contents
One box of news clippings, membership cards, photographs, and biographical information documents the lives of Martin and Naomi Warren from 1952-2010. Of particular interest is Naomi Warren's testimony about her life, including as a prisoner at Auschwitz-Birkenau and Bergen-Belsen.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Warren Spector, March 22, 2018
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in one series as follows: Series I: General
Biographical / Historical
Naomi Warren (née Kaplan) was born on September 1, 1920 in Wołkowysk, Poland. After enrolling in a nearby university, Naomi met and married Alexander Rosenbaum in 1940. In January 1942, after the Nazis' invasion of Eastern Poland, Naomi and Alexander were sent to Auschwitz-Birkenau, where they were separated from each other. Alexander perished months later, and Naomi endured years in Auschwitz before being transferred to Ravensbrück and then to Bergen-Belsen, which was liberated by the British in 1945. The following year, Naomi immigrated to Houston, Texas, and in 1949, she married Martin Warren, with whom she had 3 children and started a successful business before he passed in 1960. Naomi retained an active role in the business and in the Houston community until her death on October 2, 2016. Information taken from https://hmh.org/survivors/list/naomi-warren_33e.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
membership cards; photographs; clippings (information artifacts)
Subjects (Persons)
Spector, Helen Warren; Warren, Martin
- Series I: General
  - Martin Warren Natualization Certificate, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - membership cards, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Camp Tel Yehudah Photographs, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beth Yeshurun Confirmation class photo, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - news clippings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - magazine article on Naomi Warren, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Dark Memories: The Story of the Holocaust", 2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Naomi Warren's testimony for Kaddish School, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - group photograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - credit cards, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - business card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)